<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <id>http://pragmaticleaders.com/</id>
  <title>Pragmatic Leaders</title>
  <updated>2015-03-04T00:00:00Z</updated>
  <link rel="alternate" href="http://pragmaticleaders.com/"/>
  <link rel="self" href="http://pragmaticleaders.com/en/blog/feed.xml"/>
  <author>
    <name>Andriy Skuratoff</name>
    <uri>http://pragmaticleaders.com/en</uri>
  </author>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:pragmaticleaders.com,2015-03-04:/en/blog/2015/pirate-story/</id>
    <title type="html">Pirate Story or 3 things to boost conflict in a team</title>
    <published>2015-03-04T00:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2015-03-04T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" href="http://pragmaticleaders.com/en/blog/2015/pirate-story/"/>
    <content type="html">
&lt;p&gt;Recently I’ve been looking for some music animations for my little daughter and discovered &lt;a href="http://www.erichermanmusic.com/about.html"&gt;Eric Herman&lt;/a&gt; and his brilliant and edifying pirate story.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class="embed-responsive embed-responsive-16by9"&gt;
	&lt;iframe src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/exads7KV-Y0?rel=0" allowfullscreen=""&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These kind of conflicts actually happen pretty often in real life.  Different teams, different businesses, different industries but the same 3 factors in different combinations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="factor-1-----no-criteria"&gt;Factor 1 — No Criteria&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;So Bluebeard said, “Since we’ve nothing to do&lt;br /&gt;
Why don’t we paint our new pirate ship blue?”&lt;br /&gt;
…&lt;br /&gt;
Redbeard spoke up, saying, “Aye, but instead&lt;br /&gt;
wouldn’t ye rather we painted her red?”&lt;br /&gt;
…&lt;br /&gt;
Blackbeard said, “Blimey! You’re both off the track.&lt;br /&gt;
Let’s paint it something more handsome, like black.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Pirates made an almost classical mistake – jumping directly to what and omitting why.  Why paint the ship in the first place!  If we don’t know why, we don’t have any criteria to select a good solution.  Hence alternative solutions people come up with – something we should benefit from – actually become an issue per se.  Smart people can always prove superiority of their idea.  A few such superior ideas in the team are the perfect firewood for conflict.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class="well"&gt;First, align the goal.  Then specify success criteria.  Only then discuss the solutions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When facing such conflict a leader is tempted to pursue one of the obvious strategies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 class="indent" id="above-the-conflict"&gt;Above the conflict&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p class="indent"&gt;A leader acts as a moderator, not interfering with the conflict and letting people settle it among themselves.  This strategy works if all your team members are essentially leaders.  Otherwise this may become a never ending story.  People may interpret this as your weakness, inability to make a decision, which is the responsibility of a leader.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 class="indent" id="compromise"&gt;Compromise&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p class="indent"&gt;Leader combines all solutions into one compromise.  This works by making everybody equally unhappy.  Almost always this is the least optimal solution.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 class="indent" id="decision-by-authority"&gt;Decision by Authority&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p class="indent"&gt;A leader makes a decision himself and uses his authority to enforce it.  This is a quick solution that may be used in critical situations if communicated properly.  Otherwise it kills proactivity and engagement.  In a worst case scenario a leader may foster an opposition inside his team.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Instead a leader can use the following technique.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class="well"&gt;Stop any discussions.  Return to why and align the goal.  Choose the criteria.  Evaluate options.  Repeat with stricter criteria until only one option is left. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But let us return to our pirates.  Actually the outcome would not have been so disastrous if the ground had not been prepared by…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="factor-2-----no-vision"&gt;Factor 2 — No Vision&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;So Bluebeard said, “Since we’ve nothing to do”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Pirates had nothing to do.  Actually I don’t think they really had nothing to do.  You know, there are plenty of things to do when you are a pirate.  What they rather lacked was the vision of future, the understanding of where they were going.  And without vision people don’t know what to do and what their priorities are.  Thus they will work on tasks of their own preference.  This makes it quite difficult to align the goal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class="well"&gt;Have a vision.  Communicate it to your team.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And finally to make a conflict worse – our pirates were up tight and demoralized by…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="factor-3-----no-wins"&gt;Factor 3 — No Wins&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Seaward they scudded and skipped on the breeze&lt;br /&gt;
But couldn’t find treasure to plunder and seize  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Pirate team was not successful for some long time.  And people need a success story to relate to.  Without it morale and engagement go down and people start to question their team membership.  After all nobody really wants to have a part in failure.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class="well"&gt;Plan your small and big wins. Win! And celebrate.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Normally you plan to have the most important things done first.  But what if that important thing is too difficult?  Sometimes it makes sense to start from a less important but easier part, so that your team can accomplish it and get its taste of victory.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="section"&gt;—&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thus for pirates it turned out badly.  But a pragmatic leader could have helped them.  Recall this pirate story and 3 factors when you face a conflict in your team.  And remember – a pirate without treasure is like a monkey without a spatula!&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
    <summary type="html">3 things to remember if you want to avoid conflicts in a team. Some pirates were harmed in the making of this post.</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:pragmaticleaders.com,2015-01-26:/en/blog/2015/broken-tool-2/</id>
    <title type="html">Broken Tool #2 : causes</title>
    <published>2015-01-26T00:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2015-01-26T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" href="http://pragmaticleaders.com/en/blog/2015/broken-tool-2/"/>
    <content type="html">
&lt;p&gt;Let’s continue with the topic of ineffective managerial instruments, launched by &lt;a href="../broken-tool-1" title="Broken Tool #1 : Consequences"&gt;post&lt;/a&gt; on the gloomy prospects of applying them.  Why, would you ask, should an intelligent and reasonable person engage in an apparently ineffective and often harmful activity?  The thing is that this person is simply unaware that the activity is ineffective and harmful. How come?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="/assets/img/Neurons.jpg" alt="CC BY-NC-SA 2.0 licensed photo from flickr.com by Birth Into Being" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="when-all-other-fails----the-brain-kicks-in"&gt;When all other fails – the brain kicks in&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The brain!  Despite its unquestioned role in survival of our species it is quite an expensive thing to sustain.  An intensely working brain encounts for up to 25% of the organism total energy consumption.  At that it constitutes less than 2.5% of the total body weight.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This disparity poses a serious threat given the dire lack of resources, which has plagued humans as a species throughout 99% time of their existence. In modern society the issue of energy deficiency has seemingly been solved.  Yet even today long term high intensity brainwork can result in so-called nervous exhaustion, which is quite difficult to treat.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is exactly why the evolution has made sure we have several in-built mechanisms to keep the energy consumed by brain within 10% - in other words to avoid thinking at all costs.  These mechanisms have a bearing on our managerial decisions among other things.  Two of them are particularly interesting in the context of our topic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="the-power-of-inertia"&gt;The Power of Inertia&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When our brain finds a solution to the task it will continually revert to it, modify it slightly and stubbornly refuse to come up with any other options that would be significantly different.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Thus, in the story #2, when I realized that the current system of fines was ineffective, my thoughts lingered around the same solution. What if we increased the fine amount? What if we linked it to the salary?  What percentage of the pay? What if we differentiated the fine depending on how late the person was? And so on and so forth.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This mechanism is known as mental inertia. In everyday life it is quite convenient as it saves the mental energy from being wasted on thinking though tasks solved.  The ready made solution is at hand – take it and use it.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However for a leader mental inertia is an impediment.  To begin with people are different and an approach that worked well with one teammate is sure to fail with another.  Secondly people are subject to uncontrolled impact of the environment, so something that worked yesterday won’t work today.  Thirdly the business environment of the 21 century evolves dramatically and what is a good result today will simply be not enough to succeed tomorrow.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Still mental inertia dates back millennia and it could not care less about the business environment of few recent centuries.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="stealing-ideas"&gt;Stealing ideas&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This far we have proceeded on the assumption that at least originally we came up with our own solution and tested if it was a viable one.  However this is not always the case.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In fact the most optimal strategy to save your resources is to help yourself to what belongs to someone else.  Thus we often copy products of mental efforts of other people like behavioral models, communication patterns, problem solutions, instruments, mindsets.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Who do we copy?  People we identify with, people we believe to be successful, in other words leaders of our reference group at one time or another – our parents at home, teachers at school, bullies in the neighbourhood and managers at work.  As they say we are the average of people who surround us.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In society this mechanism plays a number of important social functions that go beyond our topic of discussion.  However on the individual level…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While we are able to critically review our own idea, in case of a copied one it bypasses our consciousness and all rational, critical, moral and ethical barriers and is perceived as a right one, reliable and recommended for use.  This is how we can come to own instruments that may never really worked.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;This is exactly how I borrowed the penalty box idea in story #2 from my first PM, despite the effect it had on me.  If I had made any attempt of conscious analysis I would have never used this instrument.    &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even when an idea is effective in principle, it still has constraints and range of application, which we overlook when we let in the ideas through the back door. The instrument wrongly applied produces a zero if not the opposite effect. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The long-term consequences of applying the idea forms the constraint that is often overlooked.  For instance psychological manipulations effectively produces the desired result here and now but often poisons long-term relationships.  Still there is a subset of manipulations – sometimes called ‘easy manipulations’ – that is widely used by people in society, often since childhood.  That’s because we easily copy these communication patterns from our parents and teachers.  Then we apply them with equal ease.  And then we face the consequences.    &lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;But for a leader the problem lies elsewhere.  At times the long-term consequences may be sacrificed.  However the decision has to be pragmatic, made in cold blood with full awareness of the consequences and the price to be paid.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h2 id="section"&gt;—&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As we see our subconsiousness has plenty of mechanisms that compel us to use flawed solutions and ineffective managerial instruments.  What shall we do about all of this? The answer is discussed in the third and final part of this series.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
    <summary type="html">On lazy brain, hazards of thinking and managerial decisions.</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:pragmaticleaders.com,2015-01-09:/en/blog/2015/broken-tool-1/</id>
    <title type="html">Broken Tool #1 : consequences</title>
    <published>2015-01-09T00:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2015-01-09T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" href="http://pragmaticleaders.com/en/blog/2015/broken-tool-1/"/>
    <content type="html">
&lt;p&gt;The longer the ship is at the sea, the slower it sails, the worse manoeuvres and the more fuel it burns.  Thus by the end of the season the velocity of the vessel can fall by as much as 40%.  The reason for this is that the hull of the ship is overgrown with various marine creatures, mostly colonies of crustaceans and mussels, so called benthos.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="/assets/img/SubmarineBioFouled.jpg" alt="Submarine overgrown with marine creatures" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this respect the leaders and ships are alike.  The difference is that what leaders get overgrown with is not benthos, but ineffective managerial instruments, practices and processes of varying toxicity levels.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="low-toxicity"&gt;Low Toxicity&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At this level the instrument makes little difference.  It does not do any direct harm and its low effectiveness does not trigger any negative consequences.  It is just that we do not have a problem the instrument is designed to address.  This may mean that:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;the problem – in principle is a non-issue;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;the problem – in principle exists but it does not concern us;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;the problem – does exist, does concern us but currently is not of immediate importance;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;the problem – does exist, does concern us but is addressed through another instrument.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even though it is seemingly innocuous, any instrument is a drag on time, organisational and financial resources, which could be put to much better use.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Story #1 told over a glass of beer by the businessmen I happen to know, lets call him Victor (name has been changed)&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;Victor used to have daily half-hour stand-up meetings with all his staff. Over time the company had grown and the meetings where no longer the place where real problems were solved but were held nevertheless by inertia.   &lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;Victor has a son. He is in primary school and in his math class they studied the topic of time and measuring time.  Trying to help his son with his math to give an example Victor added up the time of all the daily meetings in a year.  It came as a surprise to him.  After putting his son to bed Victor counted the time once more, allowing for holidays and weekends.  He also added 5 minutes needed to come to the meeting and another 5 minutes to get back to the workplace.  The result he got was over 19 working days, which meant almost a working month for every single company employee.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;Victor made sure that every project had an effective communication channel and cancelled the daily meetings.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h2 id="average-toxicity"&gt;Average Toxicity&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If a certain managerial problem does exist, an ineffective instrument used to solve it can play a nasty trick on you.  Often times the mere existence of the tool creates an illusion that the problem is being handled.  Consequently no effort is being made to search for a truly effective instrument.  As they say, you can’t fill a full glass.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Story #2, from personal experience.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;There was a time when I used to try to address the problem of my teammates coming in late by having a system of penalties.  We used to have a box you had to put a certain amount of cash in if you were late.  From time to time the box was emptied to buy beer and pizza for the team.  This practice served well to pay for our frequent sorties to the pizza place but did nothing to improve punctuality.  Nevertheless, as long as the box stood there in the room the problem was solved inside my head.  &lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;Then I had a lucky strike.  One day more than half of my teammates were late.  As I stood there in a half-empty room I could not ignore the objective reality any longer and had to admit that the tool was not working.  &lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;So from then on the box was disposed of, everyone had to pay for their pizza and beer themselves and I was finally confronted with trying to find a real solution to the problem.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h2 id="high-toxicity"&gt;High Toxicity&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Not only is the instrument ineffective, but also it inflicts direct harm, stifles development and blocks solution of the problem.  Moreover the malignant repercussions are often manifest in areas remotely connected to the tool itself.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Story #3, which I brought from Lviv PM Day 2014.  After my presentation on leader burnout one of the participants came up to me and we had a conversation along these lines: &lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;ul class="dialog"&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;You know, everything you said is true about me.  First I was a programmer, I had a good understanding of what I was doing and came up with good technical solutions.  Then I was promoted to a managerial position.  It suited me well and I took up my new duties.  However the developers still expect me to make all the technical decisions.  We have a technical meeting, everyone stays silent and waits for me to come up with something.  I put in 10-12 hours a day and I am hardly coping… &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;OK.  Is there anyone on your team who would handle it?&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;I’ve got one – he is quite good and responsible too.  I talked to him, he is keen to develop in this direction.  &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;… so?&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;You see, it’s like this: when we discuss the tasks eye-to-eye, it’s OK, but at the general meeting, when everyone is there he doesn’t come forth and keeps mum and I end up handling it all myself again…&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;OK. Do I understand it correctly that you have a thing called technical meetings.  This is where you think through technical implementation of the project and break it down into tasks?&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Yep.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;The problem is that the engineers do not contribute, the discussion does not take off and it boils down to you coming up with all the solutions and telling everyone what to do and how to do it?&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Exactly!&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Engineers do not buy in, are demotivated and you have to be keep egging them on?&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Well, it must be like that…&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;On the other hand it is the meetings that hamper your promising programmer?&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Correct.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Why do you need them then after all?&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;What!?…do you suggest cancelling the technical meetings!!?&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;In this format they are counterproductive anyway.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Uhm, you must be right…&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then we talked for another half hour.  Unfortunately I don’t know if our conversation resulted in any decision, but it illustrates well that an ineffective managerial tool can be a blocker to solving current problems.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="section"&gt;—&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this post we discussed and classified the damage done by ineffective managerial instruments.  In the following posts we will consider how they came to be in our toolset, why they are difficult to handle and what we should do about them.  &lt;/p&gt;
</content>
    <summary type="html">Large and small problems of ineffective managerial instruments</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:pragmaticleaders.com,2014-10-30:/en/blog/2014/mba-in-2-days/</id>
    <title type="html">MBA in 2 days</title>
    <published>2014-10-30T03:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2014-10-30T03:00:00Z</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" href="http://pragmaticleaders.com/en/blog/2014/mba-in-2-days/"/>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;What made more than a hundred serious and busy people to come to the sea when it’s cold and wet and moreover to pay for this dubious pleasure an average of $1000?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The hero is vigorous and active and still looks good in his 70 - &lt;a href="http://www.briantracy.com/"&gt;Brian Tracy&lt;/a&gt;, world-class business trainer. His training “Total Business Mastery ~ 2 day MBA” was organized by &lt;a href="http://veda.od.ua/"&gt;“VEDA” company&lt;/a&gt; in Odessa in October 17-18.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="/assets/img/BrianTracyMBAHall.jpg" alt="Brian Tracy Training" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Everybody was able to benefit from a seminar – part of it was dedicated to the topics of personal effectiveness, goal setting and time management.  These were the most practical modules with off-the-shelf tools for self-development.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Still, in the first place, seminar is intended for top managers and business owners.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The title of the training - “2 day MBA” - has some sense.  Brian goes over various aspects of business such as planning, marketing, sales, product portfolio management, product quality management, recruiting and employee retention.  Explains why measure business with numbers, which numbers, how, and what to do afterwards.  Brian doesn’t go into details, doesn’t give ready-made recipes – also it’s impossible in a given format.  Instead he points out the principles and approaches, provides the bare bones of the knowledge.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Still the information is quite practical so that one can really start to act based on it.  But keep in mind that the devil is in the details. For example, I do not quite agree with the proposed methods of motivation - particularly because of the large number of details and nuances in this subject.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Each module ends with a set of questions Brian proposes to answer right on the training - makes to think, analyze some aspect of business or yourself, discover omissions and opportunities for growth.  This is perhaps the most valuable part of the training.  In our group we agreed that the first approximation we have written out, but there is still a few months worth work - sometimes alone with a glass of whisky, sometimes with partners and sometimes with a team of specialists.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And like a refrain in each set of questions: What will be your immediate next action? How will you measure its success? What are the deadlines?  The method is so straightforward, head-on… but seems to work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What is at the end of the day?  Much better understanding of the business, exercises to think out and the action plan.  And yes - now I’m a certified MBA!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="/assets/img/BrianTracyMBACert.jpg" alt="MBA certificate" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And what will be your immediate next action?&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
    <summary type="html">Wanna come to the sea when it’s cold and wet? Wanna pay for this around $1000? And how about 2 days MBA program?</summary>
  </entry>
</feed>

